all right welcome everyone it's October
24th 23 and we're in our first
discussion of chapter
three for cohort 5 so before we go to
any specific question does anyone just
want to give any
first thoughts or Reflections on
three just where it is in the textbook
or um what's stuck with them or
what they remember from the
journey Oli want to give any first
thoughts or anyone
else yeah sure uh well chapter 3 as
opposed to chapter
2's um kind of bottomup approach or the
low road uh takes the more daunting or
uh let's put it this way the more
adventurous route of uh the high road uh
which is the one that's been
increasingly uh developed in uh the
recent years uh so it begins with the
notion of what it is it or let me put it
this way if we suppose
that quote unquote things exist in an
environment or in the World At Large
what
characteristics uh should they possess
to consider them as ontological things
in other words uh what character
characteristics should they possess if
we want to uh kind of re-evaluate or
remeasure them uh at a specific time
scale uh and uh consider them as cons
consistently the same thing so the idea
is if we put a kind of statistical
boundary between the internal states of
that object or the thing and its uh
external States or its environment then
it would be possible to uh to underwrite
the Dynamics of um of the of the
internal states of the system uh at face
of the changing environment given that
Mark of blanket or this or the
statistical boundary so in other words
the internal states of the system um
does not change
directly um in a response to the
changing environment but the
relationship between those two states
are kind of they kind of vicariously uh
influence uh the external States
vicariously influence the uh internal
state so they don't have direct access
but only through the blanket States or
Mark of blanket so that's basically the
idea for the a self-organized object um
and uh it's it's uh one of the main main
properties for any living thing or uh
rather an idea for uh how life Works um
I mean by life here I mean in a very
broad term and not just necessarily
biological life but it also encompasses
any kind of artificial life as well such
as xenobots is developed by Michael
Levan's lab or any
other uh organoids or um similar uh
entities that's been increasingly uh
appearing in uh many various disciplines
and research areas
thank you that's a great summary
Kristoff then anyone else who raise
their
hands um I just wanted to ask because
the the concept of um Mar Blanca is sort
of a separation between the internal and
and external environment it always makes
me think is that is isn't it really kind
of talking about uh temporal SE
separation that um ultimately what what
really says that we have states that we
can identify that are not directly
influenced by uh by the environment but
but ultimately the system is it is
connected so um it's it's it's this this
separation like you know eventually
breaks down right the signal the signal
gets through the barrier and finally
influences the internal
States there's a lot of pieces there
first to last piece yes the signals do
get through they do influence so there's
causal
propagation that can reify the blanket
so blankets can exist as interface they
do exist as the interface they also only
exist over a certain spatial or temporal
time scale and then you in the beginning
described like time in a maravian sense
and that's like a more common usage of
the maravian property is through time
like the past only influences the future
through the present so then the current
moment is a markup blanket in
time so you could make a markup blanket
around any Baye graph you write the Baye
graph out you pick the node as internal
that's the system of Interest internal
states there is a base gra um there is a
mark on blanket so that could be um
through time you could have one variable
through time and talk about maravian
property through time it could be
spatially embedded and then it could
refer to spatial temporal enclosure but
the concept does
relatively little abstract philosophical
work because by the time you define the
basian graph it's basically trivial or
deflationary where the blankets
are and yet it has attracted some of the
most heated
philosophical
discussion yeah go ahead
rore
so I want to try to connect
the formal
definition of the Markov blanket as
we're using it in this context
with what we humans seem to have and
maybe probably other animals as well uh
which is some intuitive notion of what
it is uh to be a
thing uh because we look at the at our
environment
and maybe some of it corresponds to to
these partitions that can be defined as
Mark blankets uh but we maybe see an
animal we see some system and we
identify this collection of entities or
properties this corresponds
to one
thing um and of course we can look at it
more closely and start to see more
individual things inside of that that
Collective but well we do have some uh
notion of of thingness that's quite uh
very
intuitive and uh to follow up on that is
uh I want to understand what kinds of
systems uh we can reasonably
describe uh through the idea of a mark
of blanket to give an example uh I've
heard CL fiston talk
about uh setting a a drop of ink
inside um maybe like some water a cup of
water and the Dynamics of that
um ink
drop not being maybe not being
describable or being
describable uh with a mark of blanket uh
perhaps the fact that the ink disperses
and
doesn't uh maintain
it um its coherence is what he means is
what is trying to to point out like that
means uh this isn't showing that
property of thingness and of uh
remeasuring that we we we see when we
think about a thing um so yeah I want to
get a sense for what's
what uh kinds of systems whether they're
biological or
not uh are we is it reasonable to
describe using that this the idea of a
markable blanket
yeah does anyone who have a hand raised
just want to speak directly to it
otherwise just keep it up and then we'll
get to another topic but first just what
can you model appropriately with a
Markov
blanket if anyone just wants to go for
it my understanding is that any it's
basically anything right because if it
didn't have that separation between self
and environment there wouldn't be
a distinction between environment and
the thing itself one uh the drop the
example of the drop of ink is one that I
actually really like because it shows
that a drop of ink will dissipate
inevitably but if fit with a living drop
of ink just as a single cell yes it
would be an constant state of
dissipation but also the cell is able to
extract uh quote unquote energy from the
surroundings
right by breaking down some molecules in
the surroundings and using that energy
to hold itself together and also to use
the byproducts to make more components
of itself so it kind of counters this
dispersion over time um imagining that
process to me is you know I'm a a
biologist and so on but it's still very
very hard one example I really like is
this bottle I have here oh my background
is a little blurred but if I press this
button here in this in this shaker
I make a little Vortex right and uh it's
kind of kind of cool because like it's
making something out of nothing it's
like you have just environment and you
have an input of energy that set that
makes a a low lower end tropy system
right that demarcate itself from its
environment which is made of the same
thing as as this thing and all you need
as a battery is dissipating a gradient
right if you don't have the gradient you
have no fluid
Vortex and one thing on the that know
they that that I don't know if somebody
has an answer is uh what is a mark of
does this thing have have a markco
Blanca just the kind of flame is and if
it does well it it has to right because
it's a thing separated from other
things what is the can we classify
different kinds of Micco blanks you know
like this is this is very transient it's
very thin it's so but that membrane the
membrane of a cell is a more much more
complicated blanket
um many many points just to very briefly
note them because it's again it's always
more time in between our discussions
like yes it is about the cell and the
ink here's the one of the earliest 2006
examples there's a snowflake so
snowflakes are getting whipped around
like your Vortex external energy is
going through the so what can you say
about a snowflake well it's frozen but
what could you say if there were some
snowflakes that also could preclude
melting so that's why it has to start
with a thing and a lot falls out from
you starting with a persistent thing or
a remeasured thing does a thing have a
markup blanket this is the Eternal
realist instrumentalist question the
realist language is yes it has a marov
blanket cells do active inference this
organism has a Precision estimate the
instrumentalist position is you can
model it with a marov blanket it's as if
it has a Precision variable and so
whether we say that it's about what the
territory is doing about what it has or
is versus what we could do classifying
different kinds yes absolutely transient
watering blankets these are the kinds of
things that many people are researching
about because when you actually do have
a system of Interest these kinds of
questions are just immediately the
things that you need to
ask um Jesse
uh or or yeah go ahead David
sorry okay
Jess may I just interject for a moment
to add another angle sure this yeah okay
so um another perspective for viewing a
markup blanket um uh I mean whether or
not it is ubiquitous or or just uh it
only applies to specific things is that
uh okay so theoretically it is possible
to draw uh draw some statistical
boundary between anything that is
sufficiently separated from its
environment but uh for the things that
follow or that have a kind of linear
causal structure uh to their Dynamics or
to their interactions with the with the
environment this markup blanket doesn't
say anything specifically interesting
about the
Dynamics so uh the significance of
markup blanket uh is becomes more
apparent uh when we we're dealing with
the systems with nonlinear causal
structures to their interactions with
the environment so the more uh nonlinear
their Dynamics the more uh interesting
things markup blanket can say about
uh the uh the the interaction of that
system
and it can
uh somehow result in
non-trivial um
non-trivial elements of um describing of
the description of the system so uh as
Dalton St Vel has shown in one of his
paper week uh blankets uh it's not uh I
mean the question of markup blanket it's
not a question of whether or not but
it's a question of degree so we can have
uh a Continuum of uh
blanketed uh uh if you will of different
uh different degrees of strength for
that markup blanket so again for linear
systems we have very um trivial kind of
markup blankets and as the system get
get more complicated or more complex and
uh with higher dimensional um structure
a markup blank gets become increasingly
non-trivial thank you
oi um Jesse and then and then
Susan yeah that's really interesting
what you're saying Ali because I mean
the way that I've been viewing the
Markoff blanket is I know
that there is I guess a temptation to
extrapolate like a broader meaning about
existence and thingness but I'm just
kind of looking at it as a statistical
tool to you know delimit inputs and
right it's like it's a way of organizing
inputs and defining external States and
internal States because in the things as
they are the the number of variables of
inputs is really difficult to you know
quantify in that that broad causal chain
and so that's maybe where Ali that what
you're saying about the nonlinearity is
is really interesting um but in model
making where we are like investigating
specific input output relationships the
Markoff blanket seems to be very useful
for us to be able to you know create
that type of basian graph and organize
that
information great yeah and also like
blanket only exists as part of the
particular partition in relation to the
rest that are being described so it's
not like a blanket drawing exercise it's
like a system modeling exercise and then
taking different system of interest um
as your internal State you just by
definition get a marov blanket so hence
it does little philosophical work by
itself and yet has attracted some of the
most attention so
so um so aren't blankets um at isn't
there blanket versus blanket in other
words there's different
scales and when you say partition that
you know that kind of maybe are you when
you say partition are you talking about
um Markov blankets at different levels
and and to you to kind of tie on to what
Jesse was saying art Markoff blankets
context
specific okay a lot there let's think
about a few more tangible pieces first
here's the definition so we're talking
about the relationships of variables not
about the relationships of things in the
world so any discussion of what a markup
blanket is slash does as the technical
concept it's not going to be supported
or rejected by any feature of the world
it's about the variables being related
and then the partition is just the
definition of what the markco blanket is
doing which is a set of nodes one or
more that are intervening between two
other
sets that comes into play when modeling
how variables are connected so if we
made a model of uh temperature in the
room and there was just one thermometer
carrying forward through
time we might have one model where every
time Point can influence every other
time point but then for long time series
that's going to get out of control so a
common modeling assumption is like well
make it a Markov chain a one Markov
chain where only the last time step
influences the next time step so that
was what was mentioned earlier like
that's a a pure Markov blanket in time
is that a claim that there isn't like
time effects in the real world well not
specifically but then you could at least
use that and say actually we're finding
that the one marov chain model Capt
pretty much all the empirical phenomena
so still that's not saying that there
aren't some time effects in some setting
but just saying that it's totally
sufficient for that
case so so one more question that for me
ties it up is that when you say Markoff
Chain versus the model I'm kind of
relating a markof chain to a
map yeah I think you can even go further
the whole thing is a map we're only
talking about cognitive cartography only
map and then the marov chain is this
Motif where you have a set of chained
States hidden States through time with a
markof transition Matrix
B that's the one marov property is that
is that horizontal
chain and so like you could have a
probability Matrix that is like on the
diagonal it has
things staying the same Sunny to Sunny
0.9 and then cloudy to cloudy 0.9 and
then the off diagonals is like the
transition between them so those are
some simple statistical models of
dynamic systems and a Markov chain is
when they're just chained forward in
time the Markov
blanket could be considered from a
static perspective again that's not to
say like organisms are or aren't Dynamic
just about the markup blanket you could
have a causal Network that is
static uh it's how Bert in his work in
55.0 today introduced the Bas graph
concept was with a static causal
chain just kind of contextual factors
interacting like a structural equation
model but in a basian setting and then
you can imagine composing a Bas graph
that has um a spatial and a temporal
component or um a temporal and a
perceptual component or a temporal and a
perceptual and an active
component and then when we have a base
graph in
time with something like
perception and action then that is where
we get the partially observable
mdp but like Markov decision process
was a term before and outside of this
kind of marov boundary as organism
boundry discussion marov decision
process is just referring to the marov
chain and making decisions on a Markoff
chain yeah it's an interesting top and
it's the heart of the high
road as as Ali mentioned because whether
we're from the outside talking about
remeasuring
something that's like so then there's
things that are static compared to how
we're remeasuring them there's things
that are changing faster than we can
remeasure them so then they're not being
detected as the same thing like gas
molecules in room but then there's some
spot where there is like a temporal
thickness in modeling
and then that could be seen from either
the
remeasurement the
experimental position which comes back
in chapter
nine looking like
this experimenter observing
something
or to persist in time that can be framed
as a remeasurement of homeostatic
attractors
rather than for
example the maximization of a reward or
utility
function it's like well now the zeroth
level task is to
remeasure in the homeostatic
range not to be rewarded by by values in
the homeostatic range and then maximize
reward but to directly Target the
statistical measurement
any other topics or or quote to a
section that somebody wants to like go
to yeah yeah just this whole
relationship between um value and and
belief you know the relationship between
the value function and and um know the
the function of Prior beliefs and
surprise minimization I thought
was a really
interesting uh jump
that I'd love to talk more about or to
have some people's thoughts
on which pag section or anyone can just
give it a
thought
section
3.5 page page
53 yeah very related to the previous
discussion replaces the notion of value
with the notion of Prior
belief so we can contrast the sort of
imperative to be value and so so the the
the um the base assertion to be value
exists and then the imperative to be
that it has to be optimized or
maximized alternatively a sort of
foundational assertion can be the thing
exists which might be kind of a neat
assertion because we might only be
interested in those systems that do
fulfill that and then the imperative
would be the kind of more boring and
first
level be that thing whatever it is be as
it is as um
and instead of setting up even
anticipatory so so that that seems to to
more closely apply to like okay the rock
is just sitting there the bird is just
flying okay things just kind of do their
own thing but then that's the
variational free energy so then the next
question is well then how do you
actually
get snowflakes that fly and resist
melting cells that don't just dissipate
like an ink drop how do you actually get
something to both be what it is and have
a preference or realize its preference
or have agency in realizing its
preferences and that's where the
expected free energy comes
in again making no assertions about the
mechanism that any given system actually
does to to fly and avoid danger but
giving a statistical framework for the
bird
watcher so that they can say something
statistical about the behavior that
they're
seeing and then the other side of the
coin is like the mechanistic and and the
and that's the low
road H how is the bird of the bat
avoiding danger well it's not actually
doing matrix
multiplication but it's a whole question
to actually investigate how and that's
the low road for for each system but the
high road is kind of the starting point
for discussion because without the high
road it's like an admission that it's a
purely hypothetical
space and then even that exists in a
sense
inks and then anyone
else I just wanted to give an example
about this um in my work often people
act against their goal
because the I was going to say value but
the the intrinsic reward
for proving their unconscious prior
belief
I am the one who suffers I am the one
that everyone hates somehow the
organisms values that higher this prior
belief of identity I am that thing than
actually achieving a goal that they set
for themselves so to to me intuitively
that makes a lot of sense that swap
there because I imagine that has to do
with the
um deep affect that comes with prision
evaluating your prior is good like my
old systems work my old priors are valid
so there is a high there
around good affect I may be suffering I
may be losing but I was right all along
can't take that away from
me yeah lot lot to say there so in the
affective inference work they linked the
psychological phenomena of affect to
Precision estimation so if things were
more variable than expected that was
negative AFF effect if things were more
precise it was positive a effect and if
things were as precise as expected as
variable as expected it was neutral
balance and so if there's an empirical
track record of something being a
certain way like I've gotten out and
gotten $1 each day I'm the kind of
person who gets $1 and then now there's
an affordance that is empirically not
been taken then there's these different
mechanisms to explore like Precision on
policy or Precision on sensory inputs
maybe the three is like surprising and
so then it's like less cognitive overh
good or just more natural flow to go
back into an empirical previous way of
doing it and but then multiple models
are constructed it's not just like well
a toy model was made and now this is
like you know people are going to be
using this in a clinic it's like
multiple models are iterated in in a lot
larger and a slower setting over the
years and then more and more is
understood about computational
Psychiatry um Kristoff then anyone
else um I find it uh interesting to to
think about this uh you know um this
effectively functional of functional
beliefs as as a sort of you know this is
the This Is The Meta function that we're
trying to optimize and and and I often
find it that when I talk to people about
for instance the uh the notion of Free
Will um I like to say that we don't
really have free will because you know
if you consider really your
circumstances very carefully you will
find out after um you know uh sufficient
analysis that there's usually the
correct uh way to act and uh you're only
it only feels like you have this free
will because you're acting under
uncertainty and you're making a decision
for for for the first time so it it
feels like you're doing something
because there is there is this place
there is a wiggle room but
um you know this this this really nicely
fits with this you know notion of Prior
beliefs that sort of uh those prior
beliefs make you what you what you are
you are a thing because you have prior
beliefs and I like to use the uh the
term a Aesthetics um because that really
determines you know um uh kind of the
kind of values you're going to pursu is
the things that the things that you care
about the uh the the the things you find
beautiful the things the way the way you
want to be that's kind of Aesthetics but
the the the process um of you know so
you can you can in some in some way you
can choose that but the process of how
you're going going to get to your
preferred States that's
predetermined by the by the by the
physics of reality right so that's uh
and and that's where the kind of like
the this disension between having having
free will having the the wiggled room
having Aesthetics that you can choose
having the prer beliefs that you can
that that you kind of have to well you
can't you can choose them um if you
learn how then you you get to adjust
your Precision parameters right it's
just a m matter of practice to get to
get the root access to to the mind to be
able to do that um and then and then
everything happens is kind of
automatically from that point on because
if you're a free energy minimizing agent
you always know what to do next find the
the the the juiciest pocket of negative
entropy Goble it up and and uh go about
your
business yeah I mean saying that a thing
is or or even has priors is the
definition of realism certainly a stance
that people have asserted but also
people can use the same formalism on
that exact same system of Interest or a
different system of interest in support
of an instrumentalist
claim so the framework can be used to
advance a realist claim but at least
from my perspective that doesn't make
the
mathematics an assertion about any
specific system or how any specific
thing is it's literally to the exclusion
of that that we have a general framework
Susan um so I I actually put about four
questions in the in the notes I didn't
know if you were going to try to get to
the questions um in uh shall you look at
it from here or should I go to the
chapter or core five questions here uh
the questions yeah yeah Y and and I
guess specifically yeah what what's
which one what word to what word to look
up to find it
affordances
okay um and and that yeah kind of
actually pulls on both the thank you the
question in terms of inks and Kristoff's
um discussion in terms of you know are
these can these be
learned
um okay great thank you for adding them
so Ali explains in the intro video at
the top of the page Markov blanket is a
boundary in the state space not
necessarily a spatial temporal
boundary came up today as well what
allows the agent to be statistically
separated from from its boundary as
observed through its
blanket so I take it that the blanket is
a lens through which the agent observes
their
environment yeah lot lot of ways that
that that could be
taken but yeah if we if we kind of
associate why with observation and the
chain of perception yes the
inbound
dependencies across the blanket do map
to like a lens and then also it's a
great um connection as some will
probably see that actually in the
category Theory like the lens there's
probably even a deeper meaning of this
too but for so we won't go into it but
short answer
yes would this lens be defined by their
affordances
so the outgoing
dependencies from the blanket so
literally the other side of perception
action outbound dependencies the space
of the possible actions is defined by
affordances but if the hidden state were
a person then what their affordances
would be you know the observations of
the other person so these are not tags
on the world it's not like this object
is an observation this object is an
action it's like in this map with this
as my internal State then this
dependency can be read as perception or
as
action affordances according to Gibson
must be learned yeah I mean there's
really two things here there's kind of
like Gibson Aly like what did this
specific person think about this word
which I'm always all for but the short
answer is aordance is being used in a
slightly different way in active
inference not to refer to the direct
agentic perception of an action capacity
but a little bit more from a modeler's
perspective as just simply the action
capacities whether or not they're
perceived without making any statement
on whether they have to be learned or
not we can model a pendulum with active
inference so obviously the affordance
concept doesn't need learning you can
just model it without
learning does the distinction between
active learning and active inference
have to do with these affordances so
yeah this was a distinction that that
one paper in the Discord
mentioned short answer here is you could
have two agents with the same set of
affordances Mo move up down left right
and then you could set up the parameters
differently so one of them sought to
confirm its expectations about sensory
another one sought to reduce its
uncertainty maximally about world States
so those are all the parametric
fine-tunings
but it doesn't require a difference in
affordances but it might require
difference in how the affordances are
being taken that's how you would know
that the behaviors were different at
all you could also make a model where
there were different affordances so
that's for situational modeling and then
the question becomes very
obvious are internal State parameters
referring to the edge of the marov
blanket State
space not exactly the internal State
parameters are everything about the the
system of interest that isn't the
interface so it's like the shell of the
egg is the Marco blanket and then the
inside is the internal
States because like when you take a
photo you're just going to see the
shell so that's just the outer
interface um with perception action
across the
blanket and then internal State
parameters are everything about that
thing that isn't the
shell and then together the thing is
internal plus blanket because that's
what moves around relative to the
environment
does anyone else have any like kind of
other other takes on any of these
questions yeah Oli
please uh yeah so uh there's another uh
rather simplified um representation of
markup blanket with regards to uh the
probabilistic dependencies of the
different states uh in uh the physics of
sentience U presentation by K fris
uh so if you search for uh this topic in
YouTube there are several different
presentations but around uh the the time
four minutes or something you can see a
clear uh representation of markup
blanket which shows how exactly external
States internal States sensory States
and active States relate to each other
according to their probabilistic uh
dependencies so I think that can be
quite helpful
cool also yeah a lot of other lot of
other pieces these are all these are all
great great
questions and it's one reason why
there's such an emphasis on making the
generative models because there is such
a difference between the abstract
relationships purely within the actim
fonty just the sort of conceptual
relationships and then when mapping it
to a system of Interest it's kind of
like a 90 degree rotation with what
you're connecting up connecting ACM
terms to specific things and then when
this is all accounted for that's all
accounted for then that's the generative
model but the textbook is describing
like the pure
relationships with a um stream of
examples and boxes and kind of just
different um
pieces different
discussions another interesting thing is
like the high roads describing the
imperative but the low road is there's
might be multiple ways to realize it so
just again to separate out how it's
being done from why it's being done um
Verena thank you go for
it hi I have a question and it might be
um uh connecting to Chris of the uh
question of um free will there is a
sentence in chapter three and I don't
know where I'm so sorry but um what it
says is that there is this um um when
you maximize actually the uh free energy
where you keep your options open until
you have and I guess does it mean until
I have enough evidence that I uh can
State the belief and would it be a de
demonstration of Free Will that's my
question that's a great great question
it's kind of cool it comes up
twice in the low road so kind of as a
previously identified pattern of basian
Statistics just having nothing to do
with um modeling
cybernetics and then
here the maximum ENT y principle of
Janes the imperative to explain things
as accurately as possible but also keep
options
open Oli do you want to give a thought
on
this uh so yeah I think uh the question
of Free Will related to active inference
you see because um as far as I
understand it um active inference is a
kind of framework uh that puts agency at
its Center Stage right uh so uh the
minimal definition of agency for for us
to uh endow or or confer agency to any
system uh can be uh put it put in its
most minimal sense in this way so if uh
if there is more than one way to respond
to a
stimulus uh and and uh the other
condition would be uh if the the system
or the agent has a way to choose among
uh those responses then uh we can
probably say uh it has some minimal
sense of agency so in this sense I
believe active inference models or
um or the agents that's modeled with
um markup blankets in active in in
active inference Frameworks uh they have
indeed this kind of minimal agency to
them but if we go a little bit deeper
than that and U consider uh the deeper
generative models and deeper hierarchies
then uh we would come across agents with
beliefs about their beliefs H and we can
of course continue that ad infan
theoretically so beliefs about beliefs
about beliefs and so on uh and uh the
more deeper the generative model gets uh
the more sentient or let's say uh
probably more conscious the agent will
become but in any case even for the most
simple case of uh active particles we
can um describe agency with regards to
these minimal definitions so I believe
uh active inference and basian mechanics
put uh agency or rather Free Will
um as some of its core tenants tenants
for uh describing those systems so it is
written to the core of active inference
uh this conception of agencies and uh
it's something that we cannot take for
granted uh even if that kind of agency
is not uh soal
real agency but just a kind of apparent
agency or in other words a kind of
agency that appears as if the system
have has so
um yeah I I'm not sure how
uh uh how IT addresses the question of
whether there is uh whether or not there
is kind of free will for these kinds of
Agents but um I think uh it can be uh
seen as some kind of U minimal framework
to um address these questions as
well great I'll offer another position
which is the maximum entropy principle
also applies to gas molecules in the
room and the temperature so I think even
in this discussion we've heard
some um positive and negative
attributions of of free will an otive
inference but then the question that
that we can still circle around is well
what's the relationship
between the technical and
analytical maximum entropy principle
connected to all this other stuff for
example the constrained maximum entropy
principle being dual to the
F more recently being found out but how
does any of those principles relate to
how some body mobilizes an account of a
certain biological system for example
that's even a different kind of question
Susan yeah well along those lines I was
just reading
something about metacognition and um and
some studies done um that uh that relate
um the difference it made when um when
students were actually taught how to
think about their beliefs differently in
the um and so I think that that for me
that kind of brings in the the belief
updating and the learning um you know as
part of agency because even though I
have different options I may you know my
I'm assuming that you know the Markoff
blanket can also retract depending on my
state um and you know that's going of um
hollow out opportunities
um I can't see my affordances even
though they're there would that
be would that be um you a am I pulling
those threads together correctly I
guess yeah that's great thank you just
so we can hear from everybody in the
last minutes um Brena then Kristoff then
Jesse um and I have another uh question
it's page
58 um the first sentence furthermore
active inference is largely coherent
with idomoo
Theory uh which states that action
starts with an imaginative process uh
has to been some work done what this uh
imaginative process is or um or what
what's part of the process and how it is
um yeah is there any any research group
do you know anyone or does anyone know
about um this kind of imaginative
process which triggers the
action that's a great question I think
you'd find that in essentially all
prospective ACM generative models you
could interpret it coherently with idoor
like if you chose to associate
um policy selection with ideas and then
the policy that gets
selected would would have Arisen from a
imaginative compositional process that
triggers
action there may also be people working
more on the um psychological side but
not I mean you can look it up or or post
in Discord or continue to explore but
but I think that it's a cool question
and
topic
because uh um I mean imaginative process
is a a process viewed from a human not
really from maybe a cell or or something
I guess I don't know that's uh that's
why I was like a bit triggered by by
that uh expression so um I wasn't sure
about what it was addressed here but
thank you for for the clarity I
will yeah it's like we we we come to it
from so many different way
well what if a computer program makes
new compositions is that
imaginative not that doesn't need to be
the claim that um a a human process is
the same as a computer process but if
they can be modeled with the same
formalism then from an instrumentalist
perspective it's just like saying well
we could measure a squirrel and a bird
with the same meter
stick that that makes limited claims
about different animals and how similar
and different they
are Jesse and then anyone
else yeah I I like the really thinking
about that relationship between
variational free energy and maximum
entropy uh sort of in the risk
management framework in a way it's it's
it's it's like engaging in this you know
it isn't just a matter of like
prediction error minimization but also
risk managing
predictions um in a certain
respect so that that that topic just
made me think like
that yeah it would be a risk to over or
underfit if you underfit the
distribution you'd be leaving
information out you wouldn't have as
much awareness as you could if you
overfit it would be fallacious in a
different way so you'd want to
be at the right distribution given what
you knew yeah it's an interesting
framework
totally agreed um Resa then
Kristoff um hi uh so uh going back to um
something Jesse raised about section 3.5
on the active inference side where it
begins by describing uh how Behavior
results in reinforcement learning versus
uh active inference I was just thinking
from a practical perspective has there
do you know of any examples where
um the simple
reinforcement uh learning
examples have also been implemented in
code uh to demonstrate how the active
inference approach to that would be like
the card po card pole example or some
some something um yeah Cod tangible cool
the code page you'll find several dozen
um
applications and especially the work of
um Alex shance Norse AED Connor Hines
and
others uh Baron millage those tend to
directly tackle and
juxtapose non-active inference machine
learning and and we've had many live
streams on the mountain car the
multi-arm Bandit several other kind of
classical settings that make the
comparison pretty um clear Kristoff and
then anyone else with a last
word
uh yeah I just want to say about this
you know keeping keeping your your
options open it always reminds me of
this um fantastic uh thing that the
inestimable Terence McKenna said in one
of his Raves that you know he he was
asking this question like why us why is
the mushroom revealing the secrets of
the universe to us and he said like well
uh because I I don't believe in anything
I I I entertain ideas and I I try to
apply it definitely in my life is that
you know whenever I think I'm convinced
that I I understand something that that
that this this is true and that is not
true um I look back to that and also to
the teaching of of the Buddha and and
think to myself like no the answers are
never really that simple that's like the
question of free will simply might might
not have a binary answer it's just simp
as simple as that it's it's it's
complicated it's a process and we may
not be able to determine one way or
another because it simply might not be
um uh determinable that way the fact
that the syntax permits us to make a
statement doesn't mean it's a valid
statement to make um so that's uh
keeping your options open yeah that's a
that's that's an important thing to
meditate on um you know every day what
do I believe
nothing I gather evidence for um for the
existence of
ideas lot of different perspectives to
take great
times well thank you everybody we will
come back next week in the earlier time
for oh will be
Halloween chapter 3 a spooky
Adventure okay um costumes are
[Laughter]
optional thank you everybody see you
next time thank you everyone bye bye bye
thanks everyone bye